Normalization of Database

Database Normalization is a technique of organizing the data in the database. Normalization is a systematic approach of decomposing tables to eliminate data redundancy(repetition) and undesirable characteristics like Insertion, Update and Deletion Anamolies. It is a multi-step process that puts data into tabular form, removing duplicated data from the relation tables.

Normalization is used for mainly two purposes,

Eliminating reduntant(useless) data.
Ensuring data dependencies make sense i.e data is logically stored.

Problems Without Normalization
If a table is not properly normalized and have data redundancy then it will not only eat up extra memory space but will also make it difficult to handle and update the database, without facing data loss. Insertion, Updation and Deletion Anamolies are very frequent if database is not normalized.

Normalization rules are divided into the following normal forms:

First Normal Form
Second Normal Form
Third Normal Form
BCNF
Fourth Normal Form

First Normal Form (1NF)
For a table to be in the First Normal Form, it should follow the following 4 rules:

It should only have single(atomic) valued attributes/columns.
Values stored in a column should be of the same domain
All the columns in a table should have unique names.
And the order in which data is stored, does not matter.


Second Normal Form (2NF)
For a table to be in the Second Normal Form,

It should be in the First Normal form.
And, it should not have Partial Dependency.


Third Normal Form (3NF)
A table is said to be in the Third Normal Form when,

It is in the Second Normal form.
And, it doesn't have Transitive Dependency.


Boyce and Codd Normal Form (BCNF)
Boyce and Codd Normal Form is a higher version of the Third Normal form. This form deals with certain type of anomaly that is not handled by 3NF. A 3NF table which does not have multiple overlapping candidate keys is said to be in BCNF. For a table to be in BCNF, following conditions must be satisfied:

R must be in 3rd Normal Form
and, for each functional dependency ( X → Y ), X should be a super Key.


Fourth Normal Form (4NF)
A table is said to be in the Fourth Normal Form when,

It is in the Boyce-Codd Normal Form.
And, it doesn't have Multi-Valued Dependency.
